{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "An 8 inch tall statue of Mao Zedong was placed at this site by an expeditionary team led by Wang Fuzhou [[WAHNG FOO-ZHOH]] who used the \"human ladder\" technique to reach it. The 1970 Khumbu Icefall killed various local contractors working to prepare Japanese skier Yūichirō Miura's attempt to ski down this peak. This mountain, also called Sagarmatha, was first summitted by Tenzing Norgay and Sir Edmund Hillary. For ten points, name this Himalayan mountain on the Nepal-China border, the highest point on Earth.",
      "answer": [
        "Mount Everest or Chomolungma",
        "Sagarmatha before mentioned",
        "specific answers like the Summit of Mount Everest"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Johann Wolfgang Döbereiner [[DUH-buh-\"rye\"-nuh]] named a set of triads in an early formulation of this display. John Newlands attempted to create this display, which was inspired by the observations of Lothar Meyer. Some members of this diagram were originally prefixed \"eka-,\" and this diagram once contained entries such as coronium and aether. Containing components like hydrogen and helium, for ten points, what diagram, developed by Dmitri Mendeleev [[men-deh-LEY-eff]], organizes the chemical elements?",
      "answer": "Periodic Table of Elements"
    },
    {
      "question": "At this event, a preacher became famous for saying \"Praise the Lord and pass the ammunition\" to rally the spirit of the troops. This attack, codenamed Operation Z, began after one side exclaimed, \"Tora! Tora! Tora!\" This event resulted in the deaths of over 2,000 servicemen, primarily due to the sinking of both the USS Oklahoma and the USS Arizona. For ten points, name this attack on December 7th, 1941, in which Japan bombed a U.S. naval base in Hawaii.",
      "answer": [
        "Attack on Pearl Harbor",
        "equivalents mentioning Pearl Harbor",
        "Operation Z before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Troops preparing to confront this force were told \"I have the heart and stomach of a king\" by their leader at Tilbury. This force was commanded by the Duke of Medina Sidonia and lost at the Battle of Gravelines [[grahv-LEEN]]. Sir Francis Drake helped defeat this force shortly after he attacked Cádiz to \"singe the beard of\" its nation's ruler, Philip II. For ten points, name this fleet of ships sent by Spain in 1588 in an attempt to conquer England.",
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Armada or Grande y Felicísima Armada",
        "the Great and Most Fortunate Navy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man has been credited with changing how the white U.S. public saw the crime of lynching through his reports on the death of Jesse Washington published in the paper The Crisis. This man, who publicly debated KKK member Lothrap Stoddard, formed the Niagara Movement with his fellow African-American lawyers. The collection The Souls of Black Folk was written by, for ten points, what rival of Booker T. Washington and NAACP founder?",
      "answer": "W. E. B. Du Bois ] or William Edward Burghardt Du Bois"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Operation Northwoods, the Department of Defense proposed intentionally killing immigrants and blaming it on this nation as a false flag. Freedom fighters used the yacht Granma to sail from Mexico to this nation in the hope of overthrowing Fulgencio Batista. The failure of John F. Kennedy to provide air support doomed the exile-led Bay of Pigs invasion of this nation. The 26th of July Movement led by the Castros took control of, for ten points, what nation?",
      "answer": "Republic of Cuba or República de Cuba"
    },
    {
      "question": "This orator gave the speech \"An Undefended Land\" to preach the dangers of Nazism to the British people. In the poem \"The Rowers,\" this man used the term \"Hun\" as a derogatory name for the citizens of the German Empire. This Orientalist author used the historical \"Great Game\" as the backdrop for his novel Kim. The first English recipient of the Nobel Prize in Literature was, for ten points, what author of The Jungle Book?",
      "answer": "Rudyard Kipling or Joseph Rudyard Kipling"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once performed a duet with Condoleezza Rice and the following year performed during a recitation of the names of the dead at Ground Zero on the first anniversary of 9/11. This student of Leonard Rose and Pablo Casals typically plays a 1733 Montagnana [[mon-tan-YAH-nuh]] named \"Petunia,\" though he was also bequeathed the Davidov Stradivarius by Jacqueline du Pré. For ten points, name this Chinese-American classical musician, a world-renowned cellist.",
      "answer": "Yo-Yo Ma"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man supposedly diverted an invasion of Britannia to have his army collect seashells along the English Channel. While campaigning with his father, Germanicus, this man earned a nickname related to wearing a child's version of a military outfit. This emperor, who was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard, supposedly tried to make his horse Incitatus [[in-kih-TAH-tuhss]] a Roman consul. For ten points, name this insane successor of Tiberius, whose name translates to \"Little Boot.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While a French colony, this nation's capital of Grand-Bassam was temporarily abandoned after an outbreak of yellow fever in favor of the city of Bingerville. A future president of this nation and leader of the Popular Front, Laurent Gbagbo [[gah-BAHG-boh]], fled in the 1980s due to pressure from Félix Houphouët-Boigny [[oo-FWEH bwah-NEE]]. For ten points, name this West African nation named for a commodity produced by elephants, now illegal in most nations.",
      "answer": [
        "Ivory Coast",
        "Cote D'Ivoire"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer documented a six-week marine expedition in the Sea of Cortez and later went \"In Search of America\" in a rented pickup truck with his poodle. This author of Travels with Charley won a Pulitzer Prize for a novel in which Jim Casy is beaten to death after the Joad family travels to California during the Dust Bowl. For ten points, name this American author known for his Depression-era stories of California, including The Grapes of Wrath.",
        "answer": "John Steinbeck or John Ernst Steinbeck, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Steinbeck considered his magnum opus to be this 1952 novel of the Salinas Valley, which features Caleb and Adam Trask in allegorical roles.",
        "answer": "East of Eden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This celebrity served as the public face of the America First Committee, which pressured the government of Franklin D. Roosevelt to remain neutral during the Second World War. This Medal of Honor recipient traveled over 3,000 miles in his personal airplane, The Spirit of St. Louis. For ten points, name this American aviator who did the first non-stop, solo flight across the Atlantic.",
        "answer": "Charles Lindbergh or Charles Augustus Lindbergh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While on a tour of Germany, Lindbergh was presented with various medals by this Nazi head of the Luftwaffe [[LOOFT-vah-fah]] who earlier created the Gestapo [[geh- SHTAH-poh]].",
        "answer": [
          "Hermann Göring ] or Hermann Wilhelm Göring",
          "be lenient on pronunciation"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One king of these people named Cetshwayo [[ketsh-\"WHY\"-oh]] had his cause taken up by Lady Florence Dixie after spending two years in exile. Following a victory for these people at Isandlwana [[ee-sahn-JWAH-nah]], a contingent of their soldiers were cornered and defeated at Rorke's Drift. The \"horn of the buffalo\" formation was used by a regiment of these people known as the Impi. The conquests of Shaka led to the establishment of an empire of, for ten points, what people in Southern Africa?",
        "answer": "Zulu or amaZulu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the Battle of Blood River, 500 of these Dutch-descended travelers defeated 15,000 Zulu warriors. They fought a namesake war with the British at the turn of the 20th century.",
        "answer": [
          "Boers",
          "Afrikaners",
          "Voortrekkers",
          "Boer War"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"Praises of Italy\" passage is found in a treatise concerning this subject written by Virgil known as the Georgics. Dactylic hexameter is used in another treatise on this subject by Hesiod [[HEH-see-ud]] known as Works and Days, imploring the reader to pray to Demeter. Cato the Elder describes the virtues of animal husbandry and plowing, both subsets of, for ten points, what discipline in his work, De Agricultura?",
        "answer": [
          "Farming",
          "Agriculture before \"de Agricultura\" is mentioned",
          "husbandry before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Virgil also wrote about what Trojan prince who fled to mainland Italy and settled the region of Latium [[LAY-shee-um]]?",
        "answer": [
          "Aeneas ]",
          "The Aeneid"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This god is commonly depicted with Ganga [[GUNG-guh]] flowing from his matted hair and with a third eye that he used to destroy the god of love, Kama. This god beheaded his wife's son and guard before giving him the head of an elephant. This father of Kartikeya [[kar-tih-KEH-yah]] and Ganesh [[gah-NESH]] is the husband of Parvati. For ten points, name this Hindu god of destruction, who makes up the Trimurti with Brahma and Vishnu.",
        "answer": [
          "Shiva",
          "Siva",
          "Shiv",
          "or Siv",
          "Rudra"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shiva is considered the \"great\" one of these people. This term also denotes someone who practices Yoga.",
        "answer": "Yogis or Yogini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Soviet Republic based in this city collapsed after its leader, Eugen Leviné [[leh- vee-NEH]], was shot in Stadelheim [[SHTAH-del-hime]] Prison. A conference named for this city resulted in Nazi Germany receiving the Sudetenland from Czechoslovakia. The SA and Adolf Hitler led the \"Beer Hall Putsch\" in this city. For ten points, name this southern German city, which is the capital and largest city of Bavaria.",
        "answer": [
          "Munich",
          "München",
          "or Minga"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Beer Hall Putsch was an attempt to overthrow what interwar German government, led at the time by Friedrich Ebert [[EH-buht]]?",
        "answer": "Weimar ] Government or Weimarer Republik"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these groups named Hispana vanishes from history around 120 AD and is known as the \"lost\" one of these groups. Marius made these groups permanent standing bodies and professionalized their subcommanders, the centurions. These groups each consisted of over 5000 infantry members and 120 foreign auxilia cavalry during the height of the Empire, at which time there were as many as thirty of them. For ten points, name these highest-level divisions of the Roman army.",
        "answer": [
          "Roman Legions",
          "Legio",
          "or Legiones"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 17th and 18th legions, which were commanded by Mark Antony, were disbanded after what 31 BC naval victory that secured hegemony for Augustus?",
        "answer": "Battle of Actium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a 1781 raid, a force commanded by this man spared the main house at Berkeley Plantation, which he planned to appropriate for his own residence. This man arrived with relief troops to break the siege of Fort Stanwix and joined with Ethan Allen to capture Fort Ticonderoga. This major general later worked with John André in an attempt to surrender West Point. For ten points, name this Continental Army officer who defected to the British in 1780.",
        "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the residents who escaped Berkeley Plantation through secret tunnels as Arnold approached was this then seven-year-old, who later became the shortest-serving president in U.S. history, dying shortly after giving the longest inauguration speech ever read.",
        "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "U.S. Home Front during World War Two",
      "prompt": "Concerning U.S. domestic affairs during World War Two, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group forcibly deported to internment camps following FDR's Executive Order 9066.",
          "answer": "Japanese-Americans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Malleable metal that was donated en masse to the federal government for airplane factories.",
          "answer": "Aluminum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Propaganda symbol of U.S. women in the work force now used in feminist iconography.",
          "answer": [
            "Rosie the Riveter",
            "Wendy the Welder"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Synthetic polymer used to replicate silk which exploded in popularity during wartime rations.",
          "answer": "Nylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title for people who refused to fight in the war, often for religious reasons.",
          "answer": "Conscientious Objectors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Airplane manufacturer based in Washington which produced planes like the B-17 Flying Fortress.",
          "answer": "Boeing Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Debt securities used by the government to finance war, participation in which was encouraged by celebrity tours.",
          "answer": "War Bonds"
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaign supported by Black newspapers which encouraged African-Americans to help the war effort to earn civil rights at home.",
          "answer": "Double V Campaign or Double Victory Campaign"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Renaissance Florence",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Renaissance in Florence, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political scientist and writer of The Prince who was tortured and exiled from Florence.",
          "answer": "Niccolò Machiavelli or Niccolò di Bernardo dei Machiavelli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Banking family, with members like Cosimo and Lorenzo, who ruled Florence.",
          "answer": "de' Medici or House of Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region in which Florence is located, named for an Italian people of antiquity.",
          "answer": "Tuscany or Toscana"
        },
        {
          "question": "11th century dogmatic split which the 15th century Council of Florence aimed to mend.",
          "answer": "Great Schism or Schism of 1054"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large-scale burning of fine arts and other objects considered lewd by the followers of Savonarola [[sah-voh-nah-ROH-lah]].",
          "answer": "Bonfire of the Vanities or Falò delle vanità"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sculptor who won a competition to design the title fixture for the Florence Cathedral's dome.",
          "answer": [
            "Filippo Brunelleschi ]",
            "Pippo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolt of 14th century wool workers which nearly toppled the sitting government.",
          "answer": "Ciompi ] Revolt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival republic on the Arno which was sold to Florence by the Visconti family in 1406.",
          "answer": "Republic of Pisa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ming Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Great Ming, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nomadic tribe whose Yuan Dynasty was overthrown by the native Ming emperors.",
          "answer": "Mongols or Mongolians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern city, formerly called Dadu, which they established as their capital.",
          "answer": "Beijing or Peking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Semi-nomadic people group who overthrew them and established the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty.",
          "answer": "Manchus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eunuch and Chinese admiral who commanded the Ming Treasure fleets.",
          "answer": [
            "Zheng He ] or Cheng Ho",
            "Ma He"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European religious order for whom Matteo Ricci [[REE-chee]] and Francis Xavier led missions to Ming China.",
          "answer": [
            "Jesuits",
            "Society of Jesus",
            "or Societas Iesu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Material mass-produced at the Jingdezhen [[JING-DEH-ZHEN]] kilns for export to Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Ceramics",
            "Porcelain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Crisis\" caused by the capture of the sitting Ming Emperor, Yingzhong, by the Oirats [[OY-RAHTS]].",
          "answer": "Tumu Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Isolationist policy which banned non-government-sanctioned sea trade, first instituted by the Hongwu Emperor.",
          "answer": [
            "Haijin",
            "Biguan Suoguo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This deity was worshipped in Sparta under an epithet that translates to \"Willow-Bound.\" This deity, dubbed \"of the Golden Shaft\" was a patron of childbirth despite her personal (20 pts)",
        "chastity. Though this goddess's main cult centers were at Brauron [[BRAW-rahn]] and her birthplace of Delos, a temple dedicated to this deity at Ephesus [[eh-FEH-soos]] was one of the Seven (10 pts)",
        "Ancient Wonders of the World. For ten points, name this twin sister of Apollo, the Greek goddess of the hunt."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Artemis",
        "Diana until \"Greek\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This river was originally termed the \"River of Good Omens\" by Vasco da Gama, though it was quickly re-dubbed the Cuama [[KWAH-muh]]. The Caprivi [[kah-PREE- vee]] Strip in (20 pts)",
        "Namibia was created to give the German Empire access to this river during the Scramble for Africa. This river was first charted by David Livingstone, who traversed its course to Victoria Falls. (10 pts)",
        "Once occupied by the Mutapa [[moo-TAH-pah]] Empire, for ten points, what fourth-longest river in Africa today provides the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Zambezi River",
        "Cuama River before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The loser of this battle sent his Imperial Guard to capture La Haye Sainte and Plancenoit [[PLAHN-sen-NWAH]] but was later pushed back by Foot Guards under Sir Peregrine (20 pts)",
        "Maitland. After his Prussians were defeated at the Battle of Ligny [[leen-YEE]], two days before this battle, Gebhard von Blücher [[BLOO-kuh]] withdrew north to (10 pts)",
        "Wavre [[WAHV]]. For ten points, name this 1815 battle at which the Seventh Coalition led by the Duke of Wellington ensured the final defeat of Napoleon Bonaparte."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Waterloo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "One group who performed this art form premiered their first piece, Le Pavillon d'Armide [[luh pah-vee-YOHN dar-MEED]], in Paris in 1909, following it up with Prince Igor, both of which were choreographed by Michel Fokine [[mee-SHEL foh- KEEN]]. (*) Sergei Diaghilev [[de-AH-guh-lef]] founded an influential Russian company known for this art form, music for which included The Firebird and The Rite of Spring by Igor (*) Stravinsky. For ten points, name this art form of performative dance, practiced by Anna Pavlova and Vaslav Nijinsky."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ballet",
        "Ballet Russes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Exposure to the chemical Pyridostigmine [[\"pie\"-rih-doh-STIG-meen]] Bromide led to this war's namesake \"syndrome,\" a debilitating chronic illness common among U.S. (20 pts)",
        "veterans. The end of this war's hostilities have partially been attributed to photos released of the Highway of Death. This month-long war used the codename Desert Storm. The invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Kuwait by Iraq triggered, for ten points, what U.S.-led invasion during the George H.W. Bush administration?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "First Persian Gulf War",
        "Gulf War Syndrome",
        "First Iraq War before mentioned",
        "Desert Storm before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One holder of this position advocated for the replacement of the Bonus Act with the 1965 Highway Beautification Act. Another holder of this position remarked that \"If you can save just one child, it's worth it\" (20 pts)",
        "when explaining her \"Just Say No\" campaign as part of the U.S. War on Drugs. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this position held by figures such as Lady Bird Johnson and Nancy Reagan."
      ],
      "answer": "First Lady of the United States or FLOTUS"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this province, the Solidarity Coalition led by Jack Munro led a general strike in the early 1980s made up of 100,000 strikers. The Tsimshian [[sihm-SHE-ahn]] people of this province built totem poles and hosted potlach [[POT-latch]] (20 pts)",
        "ceremonies. The term \"Fifty-Four Forty or Fight\" concerned the border dispute between the Oregon territory and this modern province. Royal Navy officer George Vancouver names (10 pts)",
        "the largest city of, for ten points, what Canadian province?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "British Columbia",
        "BC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In an effort to suppress this faith, President Élie Lescot [[leh-SKOH]] launched Operation Cleanup in the 1940s. This faith overtook traditional Catholicism in the early 19th century after Jean-Jacques Dessalines [[deh-sah-LEEN]] declared (*) himself head of the state church. Many of this faith's priest caste, known as houngans [[HOONG-gahns]], gained power during the reign of Papa Doc Duvalier [[doo-vahl- YEH]]. (*) For ten points name this African diaspora religion originating in Haiti."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haitian Vodouism",
        "Voodoo"
      ]
    }
  ]
}